ANA PAULA MENDES

Senior Software Engineer | Consultant Master's student in Intelligent Computing

📞 +55 86 99549-8253 📮 anapaula.ds.mendes@gmail.com

🔗 anapaulamendes.github.io 👂 Teresina, Piauí, Brazil

🛅 /anapauladsmendes 🐶 /anapaulamendes Updated at: April, 2024

ABOUT ME

I am currently working as a Senior Software Engineer and have experience as a Developer Consultant. And I'm a Master's Degree student in Computer Science with a line of research in Intelligent Computing at Universidade Federal do Piauí. My areas of expertise are in Software Development and Artificial Intelligence.

I have a huge passion for teaching and sharing knowledge as much as I can. I believe that information in the right hands has the power to move the world and offer better conditions for society. I am continually cultivating other women with tech mentorship. I love participating in the Python Brasil community since I co-founded PyLadies Teresina in 2016.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Senior Software Engineer

Remote

Jusbrasil

April, 2024 - Ongoing

São Paulo, Brazil

Team KB - Entidades: Correctly identify the manifestations of real-world entities in our data, that is, we work to associate people, organizations and companies with their identification documents.

Technologies used: Python, Go, Scala, PySpark, Pytest, Docker, Kubernetes, GCP, Elasticsearch, Nexus Repository Manager, Grafana.

📋 January, 2023 - April, 2024

São Paulo, Brazil

Team Digesto - LegalOps: Building and maintaining a business-to-business LegalOps tool to help companies and lawyers transform massive amounts of data into better legal decisions.

EDUCATION

Master of Science - MS, Computer Science

Line of Research: Intelligent Computing

Universidade Federal do Piauí - UFPI

2023 - Ongoing

Teresina, Piauí, Brazil

Bachelor of Computer Science

Universidade Federal do Piauí - UFPI

2016 - 2022

💡 Teresina, Piauí, Brazil

Software Development Technician

Instituto Federal de Ciência e Tecnologia do Piauí - IFPI

2012 - 2016

Teresina, Piauí, Brazil

Industrial Administrative Assistant Technician

Serviço Nacional de Aprendizagem Industrial - SENAI

2012 - 2014

Paresina, Piauí, Brazil

LANGUAGES

English: High Intermediate: VPA 880-1280 by Voxy

Portuguese: Native

Technologies used: Python Async, FastAPI, Pytest, PostgreSQL, GCP, Docker, Kubernetes, SQLAlchemy, Camunda, Opensearch, Keycloak.

Developer Consultant

Remote

Thoughtworks

- April, 2021 January, 2023
- Recife, Pernambuco, Brazil

Thoughtworks is a leading global technology consultancy that integrates strategy, design and software engineering to enable enterprises and technology disruptors across the globe to thrive as modern digital businesses.

Working with Agile Methodologies, Lean Inception, Communication, Effective Feedback, High Performance Teams, Pairing; different software architectures like Monolith, Microservices, Backend for Frontend (BFF), Event Driven Architecture, Function as a Service (FaaS) and Architecture Evolution; support to Legacy Projects; Clean Code, CI and CD, Monitoring, Observability, Metrics, Documentation, Unit tests, Integration tests, Continuous Improvement.

Business: Streaming with Metadata Processing and Video Processing

Technologies used: Ruby, Ruby on Rails, Sinatra, Python, Flask, JavaScript, Redis, MongoDB, GitLab, Tsuru, Sentry, Grafrana, NewRelic, GCP, React, React Hooks, HTML, CSS, Docker, Kubernetes.

Backend Developer

Remote

Muvext

- November, 2020 April, 2021
- Aveiro, Portugal

Engaged with API projects. Participating in issues discussions, refactor, improving features and working in the implementation of new ones, fixing bugs, writing tests and automating tasks.

Technologies used: Django, Django Rest Framework, Python, Docker, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, Linux, Celery and Git.

Full Stack Developer

Remote

Quiploy

- 🗐 October, 2018 October, 2020
- Rio de Janeiro, Brazil

Development of software for clinics (SaaS). Engaged with many company projects (backend, frontend, scripts, crawler). Participated in issues discussions, improved features and worked in the implementation of new ones, fixed bugs, written tests and automated tasks.

Technologies used: Django, Django Rest Framework, Python, JavaScript, Bootstrap, Zurb Foundation, Docker, Caddy, PostgreSQL, Vim, Linux, Screen, Axios, Celery, HTML, CSS, Git.

SCIENTIFIC RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Undergraduate Student Researcher

Awarded Research at Seminários Integrados da UFPI 2020 ★
1st place - Biotecnologia, Recursos Naturais e Tecnologia da
Saúde ★

CNPq - Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico

- August, 2019 August, 2020
- Teresina, Piauí, Brazil

Project: Machine Learning Algorithm Tests for Nephropathology Diagnostic Inference

Application of data analysis and data mining for the discovery of patterns for the inference of diagnoses in nephropathology and the use of machine learning to build a web and mobile automated diagnostic tool for medical assistance.

Technologies used: Jupyter, J48, Python, Machine Learning, Data Mining, Data Analysis, Java, Weka and CSV.

Undergraduate Student Researcher

CNPq - Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico

- August, 2017 August, 2018
- Teresina, Piauí, Brazil

Project: Application of Fuzzy Logic for Automatic Identification of Immunogenic Epitopes in Epitopic Reactivity Analysis

Studied data analysis and data mining for the field of organ transplantation and developed an algorithm with J48 decision tree for the automatic identification of reactive epitopes with great accuracy in an organ transplant.

Technologies used: Java, Weka and CSV.

VOLUNTEERING

Maintainer / Tech Lead

Open Source project

Colaboradados

- February, 2019 September, 2020
- Brazil

It is a collaborative initiative that seeks to gather, demonstrate, investigate and monitor access to information and open data in Brazil. Developing new features and fixing bugs. Responsible for refactoring and reviewing code. Managing the development team. Pointing and discussing the appropriate technologies for the project. Responsible for the project infrastructure.

Technologies used: Python, Twitter API, Jekyll, Git, Ruby, Github, Docker, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Django, REST.

Freelancer - Web Scraping

Upwork

February, 2018 - April, 2018

Wrote scripts with Selenium for automating processes like authentication, scraping content from a specific site, browsing between pages, and downloading files.

Technologies used: Python, Selenium, HTML, CSS, JavaScript.

Administrative Assistant

Eletrobras Distribuição Piauí

- August, 2012 August, 2014
- 🗣 Teresina, Piauí, Brazil

Worked through the Jovem Aprendiz Legal project, an initiative of the Federal Government. Gave administrative assistance to journalists in the Department of Communication and Institutional Relations.

Skills developed: Interpersonal relationships, teamwork, organization, responsibility, proactivity, entrepreneurship, business knowledge.

Co-founder / Co-organizer

PyLadies Teresina

- June, 2016 July, 2018
- Teresina, Piauí, Brazil
- ★ Organized the 1st Teresina Women's Programming Marathon;
- ★ Organized the 1st Django Girls Teresina, 2017;
- ★ Organized technical workshops on Introduction to Programming with Python;
- ★ Mentor of Django Girls Belo Horizonte 2017;
- ★ Mentor of Django Girls Teresina 2018;
- ★ Mentor of Django Girls Teresina 2019;
- ★ Keynote of Python Nordeste 2020/2021.
- ★ Mentor of Diango Girls Teresina 2022;
- ★ Keynote / Mentor of Django Girls Parnaíba 2022.

Organizer / Member

Teresina Hacker Clube

- June, 2016 June, 2020
- Teresina, Piauí, Brazil
- ★ Organized meetings, events, workshops.

Organizer / Member

Python User Group - Piauí

- July, 2016 June, 2020
- Teresina, Piauí, Brazil
- ★ Organized meetings, events, workshops.

PROJECTS

Owner

Ana no Terminal

- January, 2018 Ongoing
- Teresina, Piauí, Brazil
- ★ Mentoring women in technology
- https://github.com/ananoterminal
- ★ Creating videos teaching about tech.
- https://www.youtube.com/c/ananoterminal